

DEVOPS · MACHINE LEARNING · DISTRIBUTED SYSTEMS

Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil

□ (+55) 84 99922-7423 | wrms@cin.ufpe.br | www.wellisonraul.github.io | wellisonraul | wellison-santos-476592131

# Summary.

I am PhD candidate with six years of experience in adaptive systems, focusing on improving the QoS of services in dynamic environments like Cloud Computing. In BSc, I used formal methods to adapt service compositions during graduation. Then, I developed a proactive self-adaptive system for microservices called ML-Adapt, using machine learning in my Master's. Currently, I am exploring alternatives to enhance ML-Adapt in my PhD, such as using Multiple Predictor Systems to improve microservices time-series accuracy forecasts.

# Education

#### Universidade Federal de Pernambuco<sup>1</sup>

Recife, Brazil

PhD in Computer Science

Mar. 2020 - Ongoing

Visiting International Research Student at The University of British Columbia<sup>2</sup>

### Universidade Federal de Pernambuco

Recife, Brazil

MSc in Computer Science

Mar. 2018 - Feb-2020

• Dissertation: Adaptation of applications based on microservices

#### Universidade do Estado do Rio Grande do Norte

Santa Cruz, Brazil

BSc in Computer Science<sup>3</sup>

Out. 2013 - Feb-2017

• Final paper: A solution for runtime verification of service compositions

## **Grants**

2023	<b>Sandwich PhD Fellowship</b> grant by the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior	Vancouver, Canada
2018-24	<b>PhD/MSc Fellowship</b> grant by the Fundação de Amparo a Ciência e Tecnologia do Estado de Pernambuco	Recife, Brazil
2014-17	<b>Teaching Assistant</b> for calculation for computing, physics and numerical calculation courses	Santa Cruz, Brazil

# **Publications**

2023	<b>Santos et al.,</b> Predictive models for adapting microservice-based applications: a comparative analysis	JPDC
2022	<b>Santos et al.</b> , Microservices Performance Forecast Using Dynamic Multiple Predictor Systems <sup>5</sup>	EAAI
2019	<b>Santos et al.</b> , Trendsbot: Checking the veracity of telegram messages using data streams <sup>6</sup>	SBRC

# **Research Experience**

#### Universidade Federal de Pernambuco

Recife, Brazil

PHD AND MSc FELLOW

2018 - 23

- This project uses machine learning for proactive auto-scaling microservices. MSc research resulted in a proactive, adaptive solution that decreased app response time by 20% compared to the defacto baseline approach (HPA) in best-case scenarios. PhD research has been focused on improving time series forecast accuracy through the Multiple Predictors System.
- Transferable skills: Machine Learning, Microservices, Time series forecasting, Auto-scaling, Self-adaptive Systems, Kubernetes, Python, Java

## Universidade do Estado do Rio Grande do Norte

Santa Cruz, Brazil

Undergraduate research in runtime verification of service compositions

2017 - 18

- This project supports the development, execution, and monitoring of service compositions using formal verification techniques to ensure expected behavior during runtime.
- Transferable skills: SOA, Formal description, Self-Adaptive Systems, Systems modelling.

## Universidade do Estado do Rio Grande do Norte

Santa Cruz, Brazil

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH IN MOTOR COORDINATION

2016 - 17

- I created a suite of digital games using augmented reality to improve children's motor coordination. The games required the child to identify markings containing puzzles, leading them to the next mark. As a result, the software aimed to stimulate children's movement.
- Transferable skills: Unity, Android, Augmented reality.

November 15, 2023 Wellison Santos · Résumé

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>The computer science program is among Brazil's **seven most highly regarded programs**.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>UBC is ranked **37th** in the Times Higher Education.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>3</sup>Best Student graduated with academic honours from the Universidade do Estado do Rio Grande do Norte.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>4</sup>The paper was **submitted in August 2023** and is currently under first-round review.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>5</sup>The paper was **submitted in July 2022** and is currently under third-round review.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>6</sup>Best Paper Honorable Mention for the paper published at SBRC.